<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         dtd-version="1.1"
         xml:lang="en"
         article-type="other">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Slovenian Medical Journal</journal-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="sl">
               <trans-title>Zdravniški vestnik</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
            <abbrev-journal-title>Zdrav Vestn</abbrev-journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn publication-format="ppub" pub-type="ppub">1318-0347</issn>
         <issn publication-format="epub" pub-type="epub">1581-0224</issn>
         <issn-l>0350-0063</issn-l>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name xml:lang="sl">Slovensko zdravniško društvo</publisher-name>
            <publisher-name xml:lang="en">Slovenian Medical Association</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc xml:lang="sl">Ljubljana, Slovenia</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6016/ZdravVestn.2859</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2859</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Human reproduction</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Original scientific article</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Human reproduction</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of the trans-obturator and retropubic mid-urethral slings for stress urinary incontinence</article-title>
            <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head" xml:lang="en">Efficacy of the trans-obturator and retropubic mid-urethral slings for stress urinary incontinence</alt-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Keršič</surname>
                  <given-names>Matej</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Keršič</surname>
                  <given-names>Maruša</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kunič</surname>
                  <given-names>Tina</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Barbič</surname>
                  <given-names>Matija</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Verdenik</surname>
                  <given-names>Ivan</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lukanović</surname>
                  <given-names>David</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lukanović</surname>
                  <given-names>Adolf</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="aff1" xml:lang="en">
            <label>1</label>
            <institution>Department of Gynaecology, Division of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, University Medical Centre Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia</institution>
         </aff>
         <author-notes>
            <fn fn-type="conflict" xml:lang="en">
               <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict" xml:lang="sl">
               <p>Avtorji so izjavili, da ne obstajajo nobeni konkurenčni interesi.</p>
            </fn>
            <corresp id="corr">Matej Keršič, e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple"/>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub">
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>88</volume>
         <issue>3–4</issue>
         <fpage>115</fpage>
         <lpage>24</lpage>
         <history>
            <date date-type="received">
               <day/>
               <month/>
               <year/>
            </date>
            <date date-type="accepted">
               <day/>
               <month/>
               <year/>
            </date>
         </history>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement xml:lang="en">Copyright © 2019, Slovenian Medical Association (SZD)</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-statement xml:lang="sl">© 2019, Slovensko zdravniško društvo (SZD)</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder xml:lang="en">Slovenian Medical Association (SZD)</copyright-holder>
            <copyright-holder xml:lang="sl">Slovensko zdravniško društvo (SZD)</copyright-holder>
            <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                     xlink:type="simple"
                     xml:lang="en">
               <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                            xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
            License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
          reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are
          credited and only for non-commercial purposes. </license-p>
            </license>
            <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                     xlink:type="simple"
                     xml:lang="sl">
               <license-p>To je članek z odprtim dostopom, ki ga lahko uporabite pod pogoji iz
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                            xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialno
            licence</ext-link>. ki dovoljuje distribucijo, predelavo ali
          prilagoditev, ter gradijo na njem, v nekomercialne namene, z navedbo avtorja
          in izvirnega dela.</license-p>
            </license>
         </permissions>
         <abstract xml:lang="en">
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>Background: The aim of our study was to report the extended long-term results of the use of tension-free vaginal tape (TVT) and trans-obturator tape (TOT) for the treatment of female urinary stress incontinence (SUI) at the Division of Gynaecology and Obstetrics / UMC Ljubljana. There are few data on this topic in the literature. Our aim was to find out whether and how the procedure improved the patients’ quality of life and for how long, whether the patients had complications after the procedure, and how this type of procedure affected the long-term results.</p>
            <p>Methods: A retrospective clinical trial comparing the use of TVT and TOT was carried out from January to August 2017 and included all the patients operated on at the Division of Gynaecology and Obstetrics / UMC Ljubljana with TVT or TOT procedure for stress or mixed urinary incontinence (UI) associated with urethral hyper mobility (the stress component was clinically predominant). The exclusion criteria were more than 10 years from procedure, age more than 80 years in 2016, previous anti-incontinence surgery and/or pelvic organ prolapse more than stage I on POP–q in any vaginal compartment. After inclusion and exclusion criteria, 1104 patients were sent quality-of-life questionnaires (PGI-S, PGI-I, SANDVIK SEVERITY SCALE, UDI-6, IIQ-7, ICIQ-UI Short Form (Slovenian)) with questions about the diagnosis, procedures, complications, reoperations, post-operative results, and satisfaction with the procedure. Till August 2017 (6 months after sending) we received 466 questionnaires (42.2 % response rate). After 225 questionnaires were excluded due to incomplete data, 241 questionnaires were analysed.</p>
            <p>Results: In the analysed group of patients (N = 241), 189 (78 %) had TOT and 52 (22 %) had TVT. Our retrospective study has confirmed that the efficacy and safety of TOT and TVT in the surgical treatment of SUI are comparable. The TOT and TVT groups did not differ significantly from each other in PGI-S, PGI-I, SANDVIK SEVERITY SCALE, UDI-6, IIQ-7, and ICIQ-UI Short Form or in postoperative complication rate. Repeat surgery was needed in 25/189 (13.2 %) TOT patients and 12/52 (23.1 %) TVT patients; p = 0.082. Urinary retention appeared in 18/189 (9.5 %) TOT patients and 7/52 (13.5 %) TVT patients; p = 0.411. Mesh erosion/inflammation appeared in 12/189 (6.3 %) TOT patients and 2/52 (38 %) TVT patients; p = 0.495.</p>
            <p>Conclusion: We can conclude that the efficacy and safety of TOT and TVT in the surgical treatment of SUI are comparable. The choice of the technique should be based on the relative pros and cons of techniques and the surgeon’s experience.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
            <kwd>tension-free vaginal tape</kwd>
            <kwd>TVT</kwd>
            <kwd>TOT</kwd>
            <kwd>suburethral</kwd>
            <kwd>outcome</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>TotalReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>30</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesParsed</meta-name>
               <meta-value>28</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesBillable</meta-name>
               <meta-value>28</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>LinkServices</meta-name>
               <meta-value>pubmed-crossref</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesLinked</meta-name>
               <meta-value>28</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesLinkedDOI</meta-name>
               <meta-value>26</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesLinkedPMID</meta-name>
               <meta-value>28</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>JournalReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>28</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>BookReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>BookChapterReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ConferenceReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ElectronicReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>2</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>DissertationReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>LegalReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>StandardReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>OtherReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>UnknownReferences</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesSemiParsed</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>ReferencesBookUnparsed</meta-name>
               <meta-value>0</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>EditorialStyle</meta-name>
               <meta-value>ICMJE-WHO</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s1" sec-type="Introduction">
         <label>1</label>
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Several surgical modalities and a number of different surgical techniques using tension-free vaginal tapes (TVT) are available for the treatment of stress urinary incontinence (SUI) today. The TVT procedure for the treatment of SUI was first described by Ulmstein in 1998 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>) and it soon became the most popular procedure worldwide for the treatment of SUI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). Its high success rate ranges from 94 % to 95 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>), but may be associated with complications, such as injury to the bladder, urethra, bowel or major blood vessels. Transient postoperative urinary retention may occur in 8–17 % of patients and 5–15 % patients may have postoperative urinary urgency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). In order to avoid the complications associated with the retropubic approach, Delorme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>) introduced a transobturator sling procedure. Placing the sling tension-free through the obturator muscles improves the weak pelvic fascial musculature and avoids blind passage of a needle in the retropubic space and the groin, thereby reducing the risk of injury to the bladder, bowel and great vessels.</p>
         <p>In his study, Delorme reported a high success rate for the transobturator approach, a low rate of perioperative complications and no bladder perforation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>). Similar results were achieved in a large-scale study by Krauth et al (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). One year after the operation, 85.5 % of the women reported satisfaction with the results and only 1.5 % complained of urinary retention and urinary emergency.</p>
         <p>There is limited literature that presents the results of stress urinary incontinence treatment or compares different surgical approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>). This study was undertaken to assess the efficacy of treating stress urinary incontinence with the placement of tension-free vaginal tape used at the Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, University Medical Centre Ljubljana. The aims of the study were to determine a) whether, how, and for how long this procedure improved the quality of life of the patients, b) whether the patients suffered any postoperative complications and if they did, what the complications were like, and c) how the choice of surgical approach affected the outcome.</p>
         <p>This retrospective study compared transboturator (TOT) and retropubic (TVT) procedures using tension-free vaginal tapes for the treatment of SUI in terms of their success rate and intra- and postoperative complication rates. In addition, objective and subjective (patient-percieved) outcomes are presented.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2" sec-type="Materials and methods">
         <label>2</label>
         <title>Materials and methods</title>
         <p>This retrospective study conducted at the Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, University Medical Centre Ljubljana in January 2017 included female patients with stress or mixed (with the predominant stress component) urinary incontinence associated with urethral hypermobility, who were treated by tension-free transobturator tape (TOT) and tension-free vaginal tape (TVT) procedures.</p>
         <p>Patients who had undergone surgery more than 10 years earlier and patients older than 80 years in 2016 were excluded from the study. The patients who remained in the study were thus supposed to be able to remember the operation and the postoperative course, and could duly complete the questionnaire. We also excluded patients who had had a previous operation for urinary incontinence and patients with pelvic organ prolapse Stage 1 or greater according to POP-Q classification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>) in any of the vaginal compartments. By August 2017 (six months after mailing) we had received 466 questionnaires (response rate 42.2 %), of which 225 (48 %) were excluded from further consideration in the study because they were inadequately filled out. Thus a total of 241 participants (questionnaires) were available for analysis (<table-wrap position="float" id="table1">
               <label>Table 1:</label>
               <caption>
                  <p> Data of participants who returned completely filled out questionnaires (N = 241).</p>
               </caption>
               <table>
                  <colgroup>
                     <col/>
                     <col/>
                     <col/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th>Parameter</th>
                        <th>No.of patients(N)</th>
                        <th>Percent (%)</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <th content-type="table-subhead" colspan="3">Type of incontinence</th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>Stress</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">154</td>
                        <td align="right">64</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>Stress incontinence associated with urge component</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">87</td>
                        <td align="right">36</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <th content-type="table-subhead" colspan="3">Surgical technique</th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>transobturator (TOT)</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">189</td>
                        <td align="right">78</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>retropubic (TVT)</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">52</td>
                        <td align="right">22</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <th content-type="table-subhead" colspan="3">Previous gynaecological operations</th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>None</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">173</td>
                        <td align="right">72</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>Total abdominal hysterectomy</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">31</td>
                        <td align="right">13</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>Vaginal hysterectomy with vaginal plastic</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">26</td>
                        <td align="right">11</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td>
                           <p>Other (Burch’s, Wertheim’s, Stamey’s) procedures</p>
                        </td>
                        <td align="right">11</td>
                        <td align="right">4</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
         <p>Preoperative patient evaluation included detailed history taking and clinical, neurological and urogynaecological examinations. All patients underwent cough test and Valsalva maneuvers with a maximally full bladder. The tests were repeated after the operation. The severity of urinary incontinence was classified according to the International Continence Society (ICS) guidelines. Prior to surgery the patients completed a 3-day voiding diary and had static pelvic ultrasound imaging. Patients with the diagnosis of overactive bladder syndrome were given appropriate drug therapy (anticholinergics, betamimetics).</p>
         <p>Standard surgical techniques described by Ulmsten (TVT,GYNECARE; Ethicon, Somerville, NJ, USA) and Delorme were used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>). TOT procedure was performed using the GYNECARE TVT ABBREVO® system with the same mesh design as laser cut mesh used in the obturator system for the repair of pelvic organ prolapse. The suture passed through the sling tip is removed after the procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>). It is comparable to TOT slings in terms of fixation strength in the obturator membrane. It uses less mesh but provides the same tension-free support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>).</p>
         <p>For the TVT approach GYNECARE TVT EXACT® system was used. It has a rigid 3-mm diameter trocar shaft designed to maintain control during passage while reducing penetration force. The trocar curvature and tip radius are designed so that the trocar maintains contact with the posterior aspect of the pubic bone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>).</p>
         <p>The patients were operated on under local anaesthesia. After the procedure residual urine volume was measured. Patients with a postvoid residual urine volume greater than 50 % were recommended to perform intermittent self-catheterisation until the next residual urine measurement in one weeks’ time.</p>
         <p>After considering all inclusion and exclusion criteria, written information about the study and a consent form were mailed to 1,104 participants. The informed consent was signed by all participants. They were sent appropriate quality-of-life questionnaires (PGI-S, PGI-I,SANDVIK SEVERITY SCALE, UDI-6, IIQ-7, ICIQ-UI Short Form (in Slovene)) and questions asking about their diagnosis, procedures, complications, reoperations, treatment results and satisfaction with the procedure. Data on body weight and height, previous gynaecological procedures, type of the procedure, date of birth, year of surgery, level of education, job at the time of the study, number of vaginal deliveries and ceserean sections prior to the procedure, rate of previous gynaecological operations, previous conservative treatment of urinary incontinence, menopausal status and intra- and postoperative complications were retrieved also from the Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics database and patient medical records.</p>
         <p>By August 2017 (six months after mailing the questionnaires) we had received 466 completed questionnaires (response rate 42.2 %), of which 225 (48 %) were excluded from further consideration in the study because of missing data.</p>
         <p>Ordinal categorical variables were analysed with the Mann-Whitney U test. For a comparison of other categorical variables either the chi- square test or the Fisher’s exact test was used, as appropriate. The Student’s t-test was used to compare continuous variables. A p value &lt; 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant. All data were analysed using IBM SPSS Statistics, Version 24 (IBM Corp, Armonk, NY).</p>
         <p>The study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of the Republic of Slovenia on 22 Nov. 2016 (Decision No.0120–565/2016–2). All the research participants received detailed information about the study and signed a written consent form for participation in the study. All the operating surgeons had adequate experience with both surgical techniques.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3" sec-type="Results">
         <label>3</label>
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>After considering inclusion and exclusion criteria we mailed questionnaires to 1,104 patients eligible for the study. By August 2017 (six months after mailing) we had received 466 completed questionnaires (response rate 42.2 %); 225 questionnaires (48 %) were incompletely filled out and were excluded from further consideration. Thus a total of 241 duly completed questionnaires were available for analysis.</p>
         <p>We first assessed the sample representativeness. No statistically significant difference was found between responders and non-responders in terms of the type of the procedure, date of birth, date of operation, age in 2016, education level, occupation, number of vaginal deliveries and cesarean sections prior to the procedure, rate of previous gynaecological operations, previous conservative treatment of urinary incontinence, menopausal status, type of anaesthesia and intra- and postoperative complications (p &gt; 0.15).</p>
         <p>The average age of participants was 56.2 years (SD 9.7).</p>
         <p>
            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> displays the distribution of TVT-O (TOT) and TVT procedures over time.</p>
         <fig position="anchor" id="fig1">
            <label>Figure 1:</label>
            <caption>
               <p> The distribution of TVT-O (TOT) and TVT procedures over time.</p>
            </caption>
            <p>
               <graphic xlink:href="2859-en-web-resources/image/zdravvestn-2859-en-01.png"/>
            </p>
         </fig>
         <p>Among the participants who returned incomplete questionnaires (N = 241), 189 (78 %) underwent the TOT procedure and 52 (22 %) had the retropubic TVT operation. The operating surgeons based their choice between the procedures on the perceived relative advantages and disadvatages of the techniques, and, to a great extent, on their experience with the procedures. TOT and TVT groups showed comparable data. They did not differ significantly in their body weight at the time of surgery (p = 0.533), body weight at the time of filling out the questionnaire (p = 0.118), body height (p = 0.427) age or time elapsed fom surgery (5.8 yrs: 5.9 yrs; p = 0.665). There was no significant difference between TOT and TVT groups in their answers to the question »Did your mother had bladder control problems?« (p = 0.957). The graph showed that TOT-O (TOT) and TVT procedures were distributed randomly over time, showing no definite trend.</p>
         <p>Responses to structured questionnaires (PGI-S, PGI-I, SANDVIK SEVERITY SCALE, UDI-6, IIQ-7, ICIQ-UI Short Form (in Slovene)) and to individual additional questions are analysed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3">Table 3</xref>.</p>
         <table-wrap position="anchor" id="table2">
            <label>Table 2:</label>
            <caption>
               <p> Analysis of questionnaires</p>
            </caption>
            <table>
               <colgroup>
                  <col/>
                  <col/>
                  <col/>
                  <col/>
               </colgroup>
               <tbody>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Please mark the letter that best describes the present state of your lower urinary tract (PGI-S):</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT (N = 189)</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT (N = 52)</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>a) normal</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">63 (33,3 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">15 (28,8 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>b) mild problems</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">59 (31,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">13 (25,0 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>c) moderate problems</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">35 (18,5 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">17 (32,7 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>d) severe problems</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">21 (11,1 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">6 (11,5 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,199</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no data</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">11</td>
                     <td align="right">1</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Please mark the letter that best describes the present state of your lower urinary tract as compared to the state before the therapy (PGI-I):</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>a) notably improved</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">73 (38,6 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">21 (40,4 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>b) moderately improved</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">39 (20,6 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">11 (21,2 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>c) slightly improved</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">34 (18,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">7 (13,5 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>d) unchanged</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">14 (7,4 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">6 (11,5 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>e) slightly worse</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">6 (3,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">1 (1,9 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>f) moderately worse</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">9 (4,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">3 (5,8 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>g) notably worse</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">5 (2,6 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">2 (3,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,912</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no data</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">9</td>
                     <td align="right">1</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Sandvik Hunskaar severity index : How often do you experience urine leakage? (1.less than once a month; 2. one or several times a month ; 3.once or several times a week; 4.every day and/or night; How much urine do you lose each time? (1.a few drops or little; 2. more)</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>mild</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">119 (63,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">27 (51,9 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>moderate</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">45 (3,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">12 (23,1 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>severe</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">25 (13,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">13 (25,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,078</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>Urogenital distress inventory (UDI-6)</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">35,29</td>
                     <td align="right">31,20</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,292</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>Incontinence impact questionnaire (IIQ-7)</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">30,95</td>
                     <td align="right">28,39</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,595</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>International consultation on incontinence - short form (ICIQ-SF)</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">7,30</td>
                     <td align="right">8,65</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,145</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">How much urine do you lose now?</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>a) no leakage</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">45 (25,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">13 (26,0 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>b) urine leakage triggered by severe coughing or straining</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">88 (48,9 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">22 (44,0 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>c) urine leakage triggered by mild coughing or straining</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">17 (9,4 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">4 (8,0 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>d) urine leakage not related to cough or strain</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">22 (12,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">10 (20,0 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>d) constant urine leakage</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">8 (4,4 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">1 (2,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,792</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no data</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">9</td>
                     <td align="right">2</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Do you leak urine when the bladder is half full and you cough?</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>yes</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">36,6 %</td>
                     <td align="right">38,8 %</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">63,4 %</td>
                     <td align="right">61,2 %</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,781</td>
                  </tr>
               </tbody>
            </table>
         </table-wrap>
         <table-wrap position="anchor" id="table3">
            <label>Table 3:</label>
            <caption>
               <p> Complications and satisfaction</p>
            </caption>
            <table>
               <colgroup>
                  <col/>
                  <col/>
                  <col/>
                  <col/>
               </colgroup>
               <tbody>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Postoperative complications</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT (N (%; 95 % CI))</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT (N (%; 95 % CI))</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>tape erosion into the vagina</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">12 (6,3 %; 2,03 % – 10,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">2 (3,8 %; 0,5 % – 13,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,495</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>inflammation</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">12 (6,3 %; 2,03 % – 10,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">2 (3,8 %; 0,5 % – 13,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,495</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>difficulty fully emptying the bladder</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">18 (9,5 %; 5,7 % – 14,6 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">7 (13,5 %; 5,6 % – 25,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,411</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>reoperation required</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">25 (13,2 %; 8,7 % – 18,9 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">12 (23,1 %; 11,6 % – 34,5 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,082</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no complications</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">118 (62,4 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">29 (55,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,384</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Sequelae of surgery</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>thigh pain</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">17 (9,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">3 (5,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,456</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>groin pain</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">23 (12,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">3 (5,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,189</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>abdominal pain</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">19 (10,1 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">2 (3,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,161</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no problems</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">118 (62,4 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">39 (75,0 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,093</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Were you satisfied with the procedure?</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>yes</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">161 (86,6 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">41 (80,4 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">25 (13,4 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">10 (19,6 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,271</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no response</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">3</td>
                     <td align="right">1</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Would you have the surgery again?</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>yes</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">163 (89,1 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">37 (75,5 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">20 (10,9 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">12 (24,5 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no response</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">6</td>
                     <td align="right">3</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,014</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th colspan="4">Would you recommend this procedure to your friend?</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead"/>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TOT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">TVT</th>
                     <th content-type="table-subhead">p-value</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>yes</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">167 (90,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">39 (81,3 %)</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">17 (9,2 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">9 (18,8 %)</td>
                     <td align="right">p = 0,063</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                     <td>
                        <p>no response</p>
                     </td>
                     <td align="right">5</td>
                     <td align="right">4</td>
                     <td/>
                  </tr>
               </tbody>
            </table>
         </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4" sec-type="Discussion">
         <label>4</label>
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>This retrospective study showed that TOT is as safe and effective as TVT in the treatment of female SUI (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3">Table 3</xref>).</p>
         <p>Analysis of responses obtained by the validated structured questionnaires (PGI-S, PGI-I. SANDVIK SEVERITY SCALE, UDI-6, IIQ-7, ICIQ-UI Short Form (in Slovene) revealed no statistically significant differences between TOT and TVT groups. Participants of the two groups did not differ significantly in their responses to the questions » How much urine do you lose now?” (p = 0.792) and » Do you leak urine when the bladder is half full and you cough?« (p = 0.781).</p>
         <p>Regression models were used to determine possible effects of time elapsed from surgery on surgical outcomes. As there was no association of time from surgery and present urinary status, these data were not presented in detail.</p>
         <p>The groups did not differ significantly in the rate of complication either (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3">Table 3</xref>). Reoperation was required in 25 of the 189 TOT patients (13.2 %) and in 12 of the 52 TVT patients (23.1 %); (p = 0.082). Urine leakage was reported by 18 of the 189 TOT patients (9.5 %) and by 7 of the 52 patients operated on by the TVT approach (13.5 %); (p = 0.411). Tape erosion into the vagina/ inflammation occurred in 12 of the 189 TOT patients (6.3 %) and in 2 of the 52 patients in the TVT group (3.8 %); (p = 0.496).</p>
         <p>The majority of participants reported no pain related to the procedure. The TOT and the TVT group did not differ significantly in their postoperative sequelae rates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3">Table 3</xref>).</p>
         <sec id="s4.1" sec-type="Tape erosion into the vagina">
            <label>4.1</label>
            <title>Tape erosion into the vagina</title>
            <p>Vaginal tape erosion occurred in 6.3 % of patients undergoing TOT (95 % CI = 2.03 % - 10.8 %) as compared to 3.8 % of patients operated on by TVT (95 % CI = 0.5 % - 13.2 %). Vaginal tape erosion rate reported in other studies is 3.8 % to 15 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). The incidence of this complication depends on the type of the synthetic mesh, as well as on the operating surgeon’s experience and the type of the approach used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>). There are several possible causes of vaginal tape erosion: rubbing between the mesh and vaginal mucosa, mesh tension, which could cause an increased inflammatory reaction, subclinical infection of the mesh and poor wound healing; compromised vascularity and consequent ischaemia in the underlying tissue to the mesh. Pore size in monofilament mesh is very important, too. Multifilament mesh, woven materials, and silicone-coated materials are associated with higher risk of tape erosion into the vagina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>).</p>
            <p>The advantage of this study was that in both groups of patients a mesh made of polypropylene was used. TOT was performed using GYNECARE TVT ABBREVO®, while GYNECARE TVT EXACT® was used for the TVT approach. Thereby we avoided bias due to the use of different mesh materials, reported in some other investigations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>). Rechberger et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>), who compared the impact of monofilament and multifilament mesh used for the same type of surgery, found that the only intergroup difference was in the rate of postoperative urine retention, whereas the success rates were equal.</p>
            <p>Local excision, antiseptic irrigation and vaginal wall reclosure in synthetic mesh erosion may not be sufficient and complete tape removal is often necessary. Many of these patents require reoperation to restore continence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>). Erosion and secondary infection of mesh material may develop as late as 18 or more years after the procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>).</p>
            <p>The limitations of this study include: shortage of data on success rate obtained by objective evaluation methods (cystometry), and a retrospective study design. Success rate could be objectively evaluated by the results of urodynamic and cystometric measurements, but patient satisfaction with final outcome depends on a number of other subjective factors. The level of patient satisfaction with surgery and perceived success can be assessed with questionnaires, which have added value over objective evaluation methods: the main goal for the patient and the doctor is satisfaction with the procedure rather than mere improved cystometric and urodynamic parameters.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s4.2" sec-type="Voiding disorders">
            <label>4.2</label>
            <title>Voiding disorders</title>
            <p>Urinary retention is one of the most common complications of retropubic surgery (17–50 %) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>). In their study, de Tayrac et al (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>) reported that urinary retention developed in 13 % of their patients undergoing TOT and in 25.8 % of TVT patients. Similary, in our study urinary retention occurred in 9.5 % of TOT patients (95 % CI = 5.7–14.6 %) and in 13.5 % of patients operated on by the TVT approach (95 % CI = 5.6–25.8 %). There was no statistically significant intergroup difference in the incidence of urinary retention (p = 0.411). Similar results were documented by Zullo et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>). Morey et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>) reported a higher urinary retention rate after TOT, yet most of urinary problems resolved spontaneously within a few weeks.</p>
            <p>Satisfaction with the procedure was reported by 86.6 % of TOT patients versus 80.4 % of TVT patients, yet the difference was not statistically significant (p = 0.271). A significantly higher percentage of TOT patients compared to TVT patients responded that they would have the operation again (89.1 %) (p = 0.014), and that they would recommend the procedure to their friends (90.8 %) ( p = 0.063).</p>
            <p>In conclusion, TOT and TVT for the treatment of SUI in female patients have comparable safety and success rates. The choice between the two procedures should take into account relative advantages and disadvantages of these two options. The operating surgeon’s experience is another important factor contributing to the success of the procedure.</p>
         </sec>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <ref id="b1">
            <label>1.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ulmsten</surname> 
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Henriksson</surname> 
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Johnson</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Varhos</surname> 
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>An ambulatory surgical procedure under local anesthesia for treatment of female urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01902378</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8798092</pub-id>
               <issn>0937-3462</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b2">
            <label>2.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rezapour</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ulmsten</surname> 
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Tension-Free vaginal tape (TVT) in women with recurrent stress urinary incontinence—a long-term follow up</article-title>. <source>Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>0</issue> 
               <supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>):<fpage>S9</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001920170004</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450980</pub-id>
               <issn>0937-3462</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b3">
            <label>3.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Doo</surname> 
                     <given-names>CK</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hong</surname> 
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Chung</surname> 
                     <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kim</surname> 
                     <given-names>JY</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jung</surname> 
                     <given-names>HC</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lee</surname> 
                     <given-names>KS</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Five-year outcomes of the tension-free vaginal tape procedure for treatment of female stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2006</year> 
               <month>Aug</month>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2006.04.007</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713066</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b4">
            <label>4.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Meschia</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pifarotti</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bernasconi</surname> 
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Guercio</surname> 
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Maffiolini</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Magatti</surname> 
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Tension-Free vaginal tape: analysis of outcomes and complications in 404 stress incontinent women</article-title>. <source>Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>0</issue> 
               <supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>):<fpage>S24</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001920170008</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450976</pub-id>
               <issn>0937-3462</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b5">
            <label>5.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ulmsten</surname> 
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>The basic understanding and clinical results of tension-free vaginal tape for stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Urologe A</source>. <year>2001</year> 
               <month>Jul</month>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001200170035</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11490859</pub-id>
               <issn>0340-2592</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b6">
            <label>6.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>deTayrac</surname> 
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Deffieux</surname> 
                     <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Droupy</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Chauveaud-Lambling</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Calvanèse-Benamour</surname> 
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fernandez</surname> 
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>A prospective randomized trial comparing tension-free vaginal tape and transobturator suburethral tape for surgical treatment of stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2004</year> 
               <month>Mar</month>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2003.09.070</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15041987</pub-id>
               <issn>0002-9378</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b7">
            <label>7.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Boustead</surname> 
                     <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>The tension-free vaginal tape for treating female stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>BJU Int</source>. <year>2002</year> 
               <month>May</month>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1464-410X.2002.02659.x</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11966625</pub-id>
               <issn>1464-4096</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b8">
            <label>8.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Delorme</surname> 
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>[Transobturator urethral suspension: mini-invasive procedure in the treatment of stress urinary incontinence in women]</article-title>. <source>Prog Urol</source>. <year>2001</year> 
               <month>Dec</month>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1306</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11859672</pub-id>
               <issn>1166-7087</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b9">
            <label>9.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Krauth</surname> 
                     <given-names>JS</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rasoamiaramanana</surname> 
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Barletta</surname> 
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Barrier</surname> 
                     <given-names>PY</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Grisard-Anaf</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lienhart</surname> 
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Sub-urethral tape treatment of female urinary incontinence—morbidity assessment of the trans-obturator route and a new tape (I-STOP): a multi-centre experiment involving 604 cases</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2005</year> 
               <month>Jan</month>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2004.08.015</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15582257</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b10">
            <label>10.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>McKenna</surname> 
                     <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Parkin</surname> 
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Cheng</surname> 
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Moore</surname> 
                     <given-names>KH</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Objective efficacy of the tension-free vaginal tape in obese/morbidly obese women versus non-obese women, at median five year follow up</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. <year>2016</year> 
               <month>Dec</month>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajo.12516</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531188</pub-id>
               <issn>0004-8666</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b11">
            <label>11.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Roman</surname> 
                     <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Subjective outcome of 166 tension-free vaginal tape procedures performed by a single surgeon: the Braemar experience</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. <year>2016</year> 
               <month>Oct</month>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajo.12486</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27324128</pub-id>
               <issn>0004-8666</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b12">
            <label>12.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Berger</surname> 
                     <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zhan</surname> 
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Montella</surname> 
                     <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>The Role of Obesity in Success and Complications in Patients Undergoing Retropubic Tension-Free Vaginal Tape Surgery</article-title>. <source>Female Pelvic Med Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>2016</year> 
               <month>May-Jun</month>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SPV.0000000000000241</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26825406</pub-id>
               <issn>2151-8378</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b13">
            <label>13.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Tommaselli</surname> 
                     <given-names>GA</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Napolitano</surname> 
                     <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Di Carlo</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Formisano</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fabozzi</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nappi</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of the trans-obturator TVT-Abbrevo device in normal weight compared to overweight patients affected by stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source>. <year>2016</year> 
               <month>Feb</month>;<volume>197</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2015.11.014</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26722996</pub-id>
               <issn>0301-2115</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b14">
            <label>14.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Serati</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Braga</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Athanasiou</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Tommaselli</surname> 
                     <given-names>GA</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Caccia</surname> 
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Torella</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Tension-free Vaginal Tape-Obturator for Treatment of Pure Urodynamic Stress Urinary Incontinence: Efficacy and Adverse Effects at 10-year Follow-up</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2017</year> 
               <month>Apr</month>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>674</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2016.08.054</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27597239</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b15">
            <label>15.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bump</surname> 
                     <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mattiasson</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bø</surname> 
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brubaker</surname> 
                     <given-names>LP</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>DeLancey</surname> 
                     <given-names>JO</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Klarskov</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>The standardization of terminology of female pelvic organ prolapse and pelvic floor dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>1996</year> 
               <month>Jul</month>;<volume>175</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9378(96)70243-0</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8694033</pub-id>
               <issn>0002-9378</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b16">
            <label>16.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="web-page" specific-use="unparsed">GYNECARE TVT ABBREVO™ Continence System Instructions for Use. Somerville, NJ: Ethicon, Inc <year>2015</year>, [cited 2018 Aug 1]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="https://www.ethicon.com/na/products/uterine-and-pelvic-surgery/incontinence-slings/gynecare-tvt-abbrevo-continence-system">https://www.ethicon.com/na/products/uterine-and-pelvic-surgery/incontinence-slings/gynecare-tvt-abbrevo-continence-system</ext-link>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b17">
            <label>17.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nilsson</surname> 
                     <given-names>CG</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Palva</surname> 
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rezapour</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Falconer</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Eleven years prospective follow-up of the tension-free vaginal tape procedure for treatment of stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</source>. <year>2008</year> 
               <month>Aug</month>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00192-008-0666-z</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18535753</pub-id>
               <issn>0937-3462</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b18">
            <label>18.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="web-page" specific-use="unparsed">GYNECARE TVT EXACT™ Continence System Instructions for Use. Somerville, NJ: Ethicon, Inc <year>2009</year>, [cited 2018 Aug 1]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="https://www.ethicon.com/na/products/uterine-and-pelvic-surgery/incontinence-slings/gynecare-tvt-exact-continence-system">https://www.ethicon.com/na/products/uterine-and-pelvic-surgery/incontinence-slings/gynecare-tvt-exact-continence-system</ext-link>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b19">
            <label>19.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zullo</surname> 
                     <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Plotti</surname> 
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Calcagno</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Marullo</surname> 
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Palaia</surname> 
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bellati</surname> 
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>One-year follow-up of tension-free vaginal tape (TVT) and trans-obturator suburethral tape from inside to outside (TVT-O) for surgical treatment of female stress urinary incontinence: a prospective randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2007</year> 
               <month>May</month>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1376</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2006.10.066</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110021</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b20">
            <label>20.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bodelsson</surname> 
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Henriksson</surname> 
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Osser</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stjernquist</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Short term complications of the tension free vaginal tape operation for stress urinary incontinence in women</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>2002</year> 
               <month>May</month>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-0528.2002.01195.x</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12066948</pub-id>
               <issn>1470-0328</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b21">
            <label>21.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Domingo</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Alamá</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ruiz</surname> 
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Perales</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pellicer</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis, management and prognosis of vaginal erosion after transobturator suburethral tape procedure using a nonwoven thermally bonded polypropylene mesh</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>2005</year> 
               <month>May</month>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1627</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ju.0000154941.24547.0f</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15821518</pub-id>
               <issn>0022-5347</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b22">
            <label>22.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Porena</surname> 
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Costantini</surname> 
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Frea</surname> 
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Giannantoni</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ranzoni</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mearini</surname> 
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Tension-free vaginal tape versus transobturator tape as surgery for stress urinary incontinence: results of a multicentre randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2007</year> 
               <month>Nov</month>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1481</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2007.04.059</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17482343</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b23">
            <label>23.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bafghi</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Benizri</surname> 
                     <given-names>EI</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Trastour</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Benizri</surname> 
                     <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Michiels</surname> 
                     <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bongain</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Multifilament polypropylene mesh for urinary incontinence: 10 cases of infections requiring removal of the sling</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>2005</year> 
               <month>Mar</month>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-0528.2004.00415.x</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15713159</pub-id>
               <issn>1470-0328</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b24">
            <label>24.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Costa</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Grise</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Droupy</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Monneins</surname> 
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Assenmacher</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ballanger</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Surgical treatment of female stress urinary incontinence with a trans-obturator-tape (T.O.T.) Uratape: short term results of a prospective multicentric study</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2004</year> 
               <month>Jul</month>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2004.03.005</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15183554</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b25">
            <label>25.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rechberger</surname> 
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rzeźniczuk</surname> 
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Skorupski</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Adamiak</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Tomaszewski</surname> 
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Baranowski</surname> 
                     <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>A randomized comparison between monofilament and multifilament tapes for stress incontinence surgery</article-title>. <source>Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</source>. <year>2003</year> 
               <month>Dec</month>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00192-003-1104-x</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14677007</pub-id>
               <issn>0937-3462</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b26">
            <label>26.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sweat</surname> 
                     <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Itano</surname> 
                     <given-names>NB</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Clemens</surname> 
                     <given-names>JQ</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bushman</surname> 
                     <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gruenenfelder</surname> 
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>McGuire</surname> 
                     <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Polypropylene mesh tape for stress urinary incontinence: complications of urethral erosion and outlet obstruction</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>2002</year> 
               <month>Jul</month>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5347(05)64848-3</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050509</pub-id>
               <issn>0022-5347</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b27">
            <label>27.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Giles</surname> 
                     <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Davila</surname> 
                     <given-names>GW</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Suprapubic-vaginocutaneous fistula 18 years after a bladder-neck suspension</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2005</year> 
               <month>May</month>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>5 Pt 2</issue> 
               <supplement>Supplement</supplement>):<fpage>1193</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.AOG.0000157756.86952.0d</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15863578</pub-id>
               <issn>0029-7844</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b28">
            <label>28.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Albouy</surname> 
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sambuis</surname> 
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Andreou</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sibert</surname> 
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Grise</surname> 
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>[Can transobturator tape for urinary incontinence cause complete urinary retention?]</article-title>. <source>Prog Urol</source>. <year>2004</year> 
               <month>Apr</month>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15217133</pub-id>
               <issn>1166-7087</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b29">
            <label>29.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fischer</surname> 
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fink</surname> 
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zachmann</surname> 
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Eickenbusch</surname> 
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of retropubic and outside-in transoburator sling systems for the cure of female genuine stress urinary incontinence</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>. <year>2005</year> 
               <month>Nov</month>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2005.07.019</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16140455</pub-id>
               <issn>0302-2838</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b30">
            <label>30.	</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" specific-use="restruct">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Morey</surname> 
                     <given-names>AF</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Medendorp</surname> 
                     <given-names>AR</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Noller</surname> 
                     <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mora</surname> 
                     <given-names>RV</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Shandera</surname> 
                     <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>, <string-name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Foley</surname> 
                     <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>, <etal>et al</etal>
               </person-group>. 
               <article-title>Transobturator versus transabdominal mid urethral slings: a multi-institutional comparison of obstructive voiding complications</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>2006</year> 
               <month>Mar</month>;<volume>175</volume>(<issue>3 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>1014</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5347(05)00412-X</pub-id>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469607</pub-id>
               <issn>0022-5347</issn>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
