<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         dtd-version="1.1"
         xml:lang="en"
         article-type="other">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Slovenian Medical Journal</journal-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="sl">
               <trans-title>Zdravniški vestnik</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
            <abbrev-journal-title>Zdrav Vestn</abbrev-journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn publication-format="ppub" pub-type="ppub">1318-0347</issn>
         <issn publication-format="epub" pub-type="epub">1581-0224</issn>
         <issn-l>0350-0063</issn-l>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name xml:lang="sl">Slovensko zdravniško društvo</publisher-name>
            <publisher-name xml:lang="en">Slovenian Medical Association</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc xml:lang="sl">Ljubljana, Slovenia</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6016/ZdravVestn.2926</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2926</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Microbiology and immunology</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline" xml:lang="sl">
               <subject>Medicina/Zdravstvo</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Mikrobiologija in imunologija</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Short scientific article</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type" xml:lang="sl">
               <subject>Klinični primer</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Microbiology and immunology</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title xml:lang="en">Transjugular approach for zero-fluoroscopy catheter ablation of the right anterolateral accessory pathway</article-title>
            <trans-title-group>
               <trans-title xml:lang="sl">Katetrska ablacija desne anterolateralne akcesorne poti preko transjugularnega pristopa brez rentgenske diaskopije</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
            <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head" xml:lang="en">Transjugular approach for zero-fluoroscopy catheter ablation</alt-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Prolič Kalinšek</surname>
                  <given-names>Tine</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Žižek</surname>
                  <given-names>David</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jan</surname>
                  <given-names>Matevž</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="aff1" xml:lang="en">
            <label>1</label>
            <institution>Medicinska fakulteta, Univerza v Ljubljani, Ljubljana, Slovenia</institution>
         </aff>
         <aff id="aff2" xml:lang="en">
            <label>2</label>
            <institution>Department of Cardiology, University Medical Centre Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia</institution>
         </aff>
         <aff id="aff3" xml:lang="en">
            <label>3</label>
            <institution>Department of Cardiovaskular Surgery, University Medical Centre Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia</institution>
         </aff>
         <author-notes>
            <fn fn-type="conflict" xml:lang="en">
               <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict" xml:lang="sl">
               <p>Avtorji so izjavili, da ne obstajajo nobeni konkurenčni interesi.</p>
            </fn>
            <corresp id="corr">Tine Prolič Kalinšek, e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple"/>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>88</volume>
         <issue>9–10</issue>
         <fpage>464</fpage>
         <lpage>7</lpage>
         <history>
            <date date-type="received">
               <day>1</day>
               <month>2</month>
               <year>2019</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="accepted">
               <day>6</day>
               <month>3</month>
               <year>2019</year>
            </date>
         </history>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement xml:lang="en">Copyright © 2019, Slovenian Medical Association (SZD)</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-statement xml:lang="sl">© 2019, Slovensko zdravniško društvo (SZD)</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder xml:lang="en">Slovenian Medical Association (SZD)</copyright-holder>
            <copyright-holder xml:lang="sl">Slovensko zdravniško društvo (SZD)</copyright-holder>
            <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                     xlink:type="simple"
                     xml:lang="en">
               <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                            xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
            License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
          reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are
          credited and only for non-commercial purposes. </license-p>
            </license>
            <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                     xlink:type="simple"
                     xml:lang="sl">
               <license-p>To je članek z odprtim dostopom, ki ga lahko uporabite pod pogoji iz
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                            xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialno
            licence</ext-link>. ki dovoljuje distribucijo, predelavo ali
          prilagoditev, ter gradijo na njem, v nekomercialne namene, z navedbo avtorja
          in izvirnega dela.</license-p>
            </license>
         </permissions>
         <abstract xml:lang="en">
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>We present a case of successful zero-fluoroscopy catheter ablation (CA) of the right anterolateral accessory pathway (AP) via a transjugular approach in an 18-year-old patient with a congenital agenesis of inferior vena cava (IVC). A three-dimensional (3D) electroanatomic mapping (EAM) system and intracardiac echocardiography (ICE) were used to navigate the catheters in the heart.</p>
         </abstract>
         <trans-abstract xml:lang="sl">
            <title>Izvleček</title>
            <p>Predstavljamo primer uspešne katetrske ablacije desne anterolateralne akcesorne poti pri 18- letnem bolniku z agenezijo spodnje votle vene preko transjugularnega pristopa brez rentgenske diaskopije. Za usmerjanje katetrov v srcu smo uporabili tridimenzionalno mapiranje in znotrajsrčno ultrazvočno kardiografijo.</p>
         </trans-abstract>
         <kwd-group xml:lang="sl">
            <kwd>ničelna rentgenska diaskopija</kwd>
            <kwd>transjugularni pristop</kwd>
            <kwd>sindrom Wolff-Parkinson-White</kwd>
            <kwd>agenezija spodnje votle vene</kwd>
            <kwd>radiofrekvenčna ablacija</kwd>
            <kwd>znotrajsrčna ehokardiografija</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
            <kwd>Zero-fluoroscopy</kwd>
            <kwd>transjugular approach</kwd>
            <kwd>Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome</kwd>
            <kwd>agenesis of inferior vena cava</kwd>
            <kwd>radiofrequency ablation</kwd>
            <kwd>intracardiac echocardiography</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s1" sec-type="Introduction">
         <label>1</label>
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Usually, the catheter ablation (CA) is performed via a transfemoral approach. In the transfemoral approach, the femoral vein is punctured and the catheters are then advanced into the body and to the heart through the femoral vein and inferior vena cava (IVC). The advancement of the catheters to the heart can be difficult or impossible in patients with congenital IVC anomalies. Other alternative approach for CA in such patients is the transjugular approach. The transjugular approach is done through a puncture of the internal jugular vein. The catheters are then advanced through the puncture into the vein and through the superior vena cava into the heart.</p>
         <p>During CA, fluoroscopy is commonly used for visualization and guidance of the catheters in the heart. New methods have been suggested to avoid harmful effects of the radiation exposure to the patient, as well as to the operator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). One of the methods is zero-fluoroscopy approach, where no fluoroscopy is used during CA. Visualization and guidance of the catheters is done by the help of the three-dimensional (3D) electroanatomic mapping (EAM) system and ICE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2" sec-type="Case presentation">
         <label>2</label>
         <title>Case presentation</title>
         <p>An 18-year-old man with congenital agenesis of IVC and structurally normal heart was admitted to our department for CA due to Wolff-Parkinson-White (WPW) syndrome. The 12-lead ECG suggested right anterolateral accessory pathway (AP) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>A).</p>
         <fig position="anchor" id="fig1">
            <label>Figure 1:</label>
            <caption>
               <p/>
               <p>A: A 12-lead ECG showing a ventricular pre-excitation associated with right anterolateral AP.</p>
               <p>B: A 3D EAM showing ventricular activation during sinus rhythm. The white area represents the earliest and the purple area the latest ventricular activation. Red dot represents the site of radiofrequency ablation. Yellow dot marks the site of His potential recording. White dots mark an approximate location of the tricuspid annulus.</p>
               <p>C: A recording of intracardiac potentials during the successful ablation. Potential in the channel ABL 1–2 (distal electrode of the ablation catheter) is recorded 36 ms before the start of the delta wave in the first part of the recording. The second part of the recording shows a QRS complex without pre-excitation and delay between the atrial and ventricular potential in the channel ABL 1–2 as evidence of the loss of AP conduction.</p>
               <p>D: An image of ICE during the ablation showing the position of ablation catheter in the heart. RA – right atrium; RV – right ventricle; abl – ablation catheter; the arrow is pointing to the tip of the ablation catheter positioned at the ventricular aspect of the anterolateral part of the tricuspid annulus.</p>
            </caption>
            <p>
               <graphic xlink:href="2926-web-resources/image/zdravvestn-2926-en-01.png"/>
            </p>
         </fig>
         <p>The procedure was performed under conscious sedation. We performed two ultrasound-guided percutaneous punctures of the right internal jugular vein and navigated catheters by the use of 3D EAM system. A 4-polar non-steerable diagnostic catheter was inserted into the coronary sinus and a non-irrigated ablation catheter into the right ventricle. Mapping during sinus rhythm confirmed the earliest ventricular activation at the anterolateral part of the tricuspid annulus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>B). Radiofrequency ablation of the site with 30 W terminated the ventricular pre-excitation and conduction over the AP within 3 seconds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>C). During the procedure we used ICE to navigate and ensure the stability of the ablation catheter at the ablation site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>D). No fluoroscopy was used at any time during the procedure. The procedure lasted for 135 minutes. There were no procedure-related complications and the patient was discharged from the hospital the next day. Pre-excitation was no longer present on the 12 lead ECG.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3" sec-type="Discussion">
         <label>3</label>
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>Supraventricular tachycardia (SVT) is the most common cardiac arrhythmia in children requiring therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). WPW syndrome is the most common type of SVT in adolescent population with a prevalence of 1.5 per 1000 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). This group of patients is at risk of sudden cardiac death, which is estimated at 2 per 1000 patient years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). The recommended treatment for patients with WPW syndrome is radiofrequency CA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>).</p>
         <p>The patient in our case report had a congenital agenesis of IVC – a rare congenital anomaly of IVC affecting up to 1 % of general population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). The absence of the IVC precluded the transfemoral approach, and the transjugular approach was chosen as an alternative. Recently, a case series of CA of right-sided AP anterior and anterolateral AP via a transjugular approach in paediatric population with short fluoroscopy times and doses was published. They reported a high acute and long-term success rate, as well as no complications related to the procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>).</p>
         <p>Although fluoroscopy can be an effective way to visualize and guide the catheters in the heart, it also exposes the patients and the operator to non-negligible ionizing radiation. Recent epidemiological studies show that even low doses of ionizing radiation can be harmful and no safe-dose limit exists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). Paediatric patients are at a higher risk of potentially harmful effects of ionizing radiation exposure – estimated at a four times higher than in a 50-year old male patient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). For the operator, the average exposure is around 5 mSV with a typical cumulative lifetime risk on the order of magnitude of 1 cancer per 100 exposed subjects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>). Recent observational case series observed a disproportionate number of tumours in the left side of the brain – the region known to be more exposed to ionizing radiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4" sec-type="Conclusion">
         <label>4</label>
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>To our knowledge this is the first case report to confirm the feasibility of successful ablation of a right-sided anterolateral AP via a transjugular approach without any use of fluoroscopy. A combination of 3D EAM system and ICE can be used to ensure both the correct position and stability of the ablation catheter in the heart. In addition, the fluoroless procedure enables avoidance of potential harmful effects of fluoroscopy exposure for the patient and the operator.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <ref id="b1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <collab>Committee to Assess Health Risks from Exposure to Low Levels of Ionizing Radiation</collab>; 
                        <collab>Nuclear and Radiation Studies Board, Division on Earth and Life Studies, National Research Council of the National Academies</collab>.
                    </person-group>. 
                    <source>Health Risks From Exposure to Low Levels of Ionizing Radiation: BEIR VII Phase 2</source>. 
                    <publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc>: 
                    <publisher-name>The National Academies Press</publisher-name>; 
                    <year>2006</year>.
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Haegeli</surname>
                     <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stutz</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mohsen</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wolber</surname>
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brunckhorst</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>On</surname>
                     <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <etal>et al.</etal>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Feasibility of zero or near zero fluoroscopy during catheter ablation procedures</article-title>. 
                    <source>Cardiol J</source>. 
                    <year>2018</year>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29611170</pub-id>
                    <issn>1897-5593</issn>                     
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book-chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>VanHare</surname>
                     <given-names>GF</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <chapter-title>Clinical paediatric arrhythmias</chapter-title>.
                    <comment>In</comment>: 
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gillette</surname>
                     <given-names>PC</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Garson</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <role>editors</role>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <source>Supraventricular Tachycardia</source>. 
                    <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
                    <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: 
                    <publisher-name>WB Saunders company</publisher-name>; 
                    <year>1999</year>. pp. 
                    <fpage>97</fpage>–
                    <lpage>118</lpage>.
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Munger</surname>
                     <given-names>TM</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Packer</surname>
                     <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hammill</surname>
                     <given-names>SC</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Feldman</surname>
                     <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bailey</surname>
                     <given-names>KR</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ballard</surname>
                     <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <etal>et al.</etal>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>A population study of the natural history of Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome in Olmsted County, Minnesota, 1953-1989</article-title>. 
                    <source>Circulation</source>. 
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <month>Mar</month>;
                    <volume>87</volume>(
                    <issue>3</issue>):
                    <fpage>866</fpage>–
                    <lpage>73</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.87.3.866</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8443907</pub-id>
                    <issn>0009-7322</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Teo</surname>
                     <given-names>WS</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Klein</surname>
                     <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Yee</surname>
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Sudden cardiac death in the Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome</article-title>. 
                    <source>Singapore Med J</source>. 
                    <year>1992</year>
                    <month>Jun</month>;
                    <volume>33</volume>(
                    <issue>3</issue>):
                    <fpage>247</fpage>–
                    <lpage>51</lpage>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1631581</pub-id>
                    <issn>0037-5675</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Garson</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                     <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kanter</surname>
                     <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Management of the child with Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome and supraventricular tachycardia: model for cost effectiveness</article-title>. 
                    <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source>. 
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <month>Nov</month>;
                    <volume>8</volume>(
                    <issue>11</issue>):
                    <fpage>1320</fpage>–
                    <lpage>6</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1540-8167.1997.tb01024.x</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9395176</pub-id>
                    <issn>1045-3873</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sneed</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hamdallah</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sardi</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Absence of the retrohepatic inferior vena cava: what the surgeon should know</article-title>. 
                    <source>Am Surg</source>. 
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <month>Jun</month>;
                    <volume>71</volume>(
                    <issue>6</issue>):
                    <fpage>502</fpage>–
                    <lpage>4</lpage>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16044930</pub-id>
                    <issn>0003-1348</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ergül</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Özgür</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sahin</surname>
                     <given-names>GT</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kafali</surname>
                     <given-names>HC</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Celebi</surname>
                     <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bay</surname>
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <etal>et al.</etal>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>The transjugular approach: an alternative route to improve ablation success in right anteriorly and anterolaterally-located supraventricular tachycardia substrates in children</article-title>. 
                    <source>Pediatr Cardiol</source>. 
                    <year>2018</year>; 
                    <comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30244304</pub-id>
                    <issn>0172-0643</issn>                     
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Andreassi</surname>
                     <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Cioppa</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Manfredi</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Neri</surname>
                     <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Foffa</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Picano</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>N-acetyl cysteine reduces chromosomal DNA damage in circulating lymphocytes during cardiac catheterization procedures: a pilot study</article-title>. 
                    <source>Int J Cardiol</source>. 
                    <year>2012</year>
                    <month>Nov</month>;
                    <volume>161</volume>(
                    <issue>2</issue>):
                    <fpage>93</fpage>–
                    <lpage>6</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2011.05.001</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605919</pub-id>
                    <issn>0167-5273</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Venneri</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rossi</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Botto</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Andreassi</surname>
                     <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Salcone</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Emad</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <etal>et al.</etal>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Cancer risk from professional exposure in staff working in cardiac catheterization laboratory: insights from the National Research Council’s Biological Effects of Ionizing Radiation VII Report</article-title>. 
                    <source>Am Heart J</source>. 
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <month>Jan</month>;
                    <volume>157</volume>(
                    <issue>1</issue>):
                    <fpage>118</fpage>–
                    <lpage>24</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ahj.2008.08.009</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19081407</pub-id>
                    <issn>0002-8703</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Roguin</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>CardioPulse. Radiation in cardiology: can’t live without it!:  using appropriate shielding, keeping a distance as safely as possible and reducing radiation time are essential principles for radiation reduction</article-title>. 
                    <source>Eur Heart J</source>. 
                    <year>2014</year>
                    <month>Mar</month>;
                    <volume>35</volume>(
                    <issue>10</issue>):
                    <fpage>599</fpage>–
                    <lpage>600</lpage>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24609722</pub-id>
                    <issn>1522-9645</issn>                     
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
