<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         dtd-version="1.1"
         xml:lang="en"
         article-type="other">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">Zdrav Vestn</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Slovenian Medical Journal</journal-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="sl">
               <trans-title>Zdravniški vestnik</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
            <abbrev-journal-title>Zdrav Vestn</abbrev-journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn publication-format="ppub" pub-type="ppub">1318-0347</issn>
         <issn publication-format="epub" pub-type="epub">1581-0224</issn>
         <issn-l>0350-0063</issn-l>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name xml:lang="sl">Slovensko zdravniško društvo</publisher-name>
            <publisher-name xml:lang="en">Slovenian Medical Association</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc xml:lang="sl">Ljubljana, Slovenia</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6016/ZdravVestn.2963</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2963</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Neurobiology</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline" xml:lang="sl">
               <subject>Medicina/Zdravstvo</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Nevrobiologija</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Short scientific article</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type" xml:lang="sl">
               <subject>Klinični primer</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading" xml:lang="en">
               <subject>Neurobiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title xml:lang="en">Posterior intraorbital bullet</article-title>
            <trans-title-group>
               <trans-title xml:lang="sl">Posteriorni intraorbitalni izstrelek</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
            <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head" xml:lang="en">Posterior intraorbital bullet</alt-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bašković</surname>
                  <given-names>Marko</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Striber</surname>
                  <given-names>Neda</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gjurašin</surname>
                  <given-names>Miroslav</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="aff1" xml:lang="en">
            <label>1</label>
            <institution>Department of pediatric surgery, Children's hospital Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia</institution>
         </aff>
         <aff id="aff2" xml:lang="en">
            <label>2</label>
            <institution>Department of ophthalmology, Children's hospital Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia</institution>
         </aff>
         <aff id="aff3" xml:lang="en">
            <label>3</label>
            <institution>Department of neurosurgery, Children's hospital Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia</institution>
         </aff>
         <author-notes>
            <fn fn-type="conflict" xml:lang="en">
               <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict" xml:lang="sl">
               <p>Avtorji so izjavili, da ne obstajajo nobeni konkurenčni interesi.</p>
            </fn>
            <corresp id="corr">Marko Bašković, e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple"/>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>Volume</month>
            <year>89</year>
         </pub-date>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub">
            <month>Volume</month>
            <year>89</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>89</volume>
         <issue>Epub ahead of print</issue>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>4</lpage>
         <history>
            <date date-type="received">
               <day>16</day>
               <month>6</month>
               <year>2019</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="accepted">
               <day>15</day>
               <month>8</month>
               <year>2019</year>
            </date>
         </history>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement xml:lang="en">Copyright © 2020, Slovenian Medical Association (SZD)</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-statement xml:lang="sl">© 2020, Slovensko zdravniško društvo (SZD)</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder xml:lang="en">Slovenian Medical Association (SZD)</copyright-holder>
            <copyright-holder xml:lang="sl">Slovensko zdravniško društvo (SZD)</copyright-holder>
            <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                     xlink:type="simple"
                     xml:lang="en">
               <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                            xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
            License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
          reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are
          credited and only for non-commercial purposes. </license-p>
            </license>
            <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                     xlink:type="simple"
                     xml:lang="sl">
               <license-p>To je članek z odprtim dostopom, ki ga lahko uporabite pod pogoji iz
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"
                            xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Priznanje avtorstva-Nekomercialno
            licence</ext-link>. ki dovoljuje distribucijo, predelavo ali
          prilagoditev, ter gradijo na njem, v nekomercialne namene, z navedbo avtorja
          in izvirnega dela.</license-p>
            </license>
         </permissions>
         <abstract xml:lang="en">
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>Indeed, nowadays there is no clear agreement about the ideal treatment (conservative or surgical) of posterior intraorbital bullet in view of possible serious damage to vital structures such as the possibility of compromising the optic nerve. The decision to remove an orbital foreign body should always be made on an individual basis, with due consideration of the benefits and dangers of surgery.</p>
         </abstract>
         <trans-abstract xml:lang="sl">
            <title>Izvleček</title>
            <p>Danes ni jasnega dogovora o idealni obravnavi (konzervativno ali kirurško) posteriornega intraorbitalnega izstrelka glede na možno resno poškodbo vitalnih struktur, kot je možnost ogrožanja optičnega živca. Odločitev o odstranitvi orbitalnega tujega telesa mora biti vedno na individualni osnovi ob ustreznem premisleku o koristih in nevarnostih operacije.</p>
         </trans-abstract>
         <kwd-group xml:lang="sl">
            <kwd>izstrelek</kwd>
            <kwd>orbita</kwd>
            <kwd>strelna rana</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
            <kwd>bullet</kwd>
            <kwd>orbit</kwd>
            <kwd>gunshot wound</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s1" sec-type="Introduction">
         <label>1</label>
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Gunshot wounds can cause serious organ damage. Prognosis depends on numerous components, including the size, kinetic energy, entry and trajectory of the penetrating object (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). Guns create three crucial wound types: penetrating, perforating, and avulsion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). Detainment of a bullet between the orbit and the eyeball is due to either a low-velocity bullet, or a high-velocity bullet, shot from a long distance or slowed by intermediate impacts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). We show the case of a twelve-year-old girl with a posterior infraorbital bullet, who was wounded by an air rifle.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2" sec-type="Case report">
         <label>2</label>
         <title>Case report</title>
         <p>A 12-year-old girl presented to the emergency department after being shot with a .177 (4.5 mm) air gun stuffed diabolo pellet. The pellet shot the girl’s left infraorbital. The entry wound in a size of 3 mm was barely noticeable, located 0.9 cm below the lower eyelid and 3.6 cm laterally to the nasal sidewall. Before the accident, her ocular history included diplopia (anamnestically, the girl’s mother said that the girl had diplopia before but she was never referred to an ophthalmologist). At the first examination, the mydriasis and ptosis on the left eye were noticed. The left pupil did not react to the light. The right eye status was normal. After an emergency craniogram was performed, a foreign body was verified in the projection of the left orbit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). Upon the arrival of an ophthalmologist, the eye status was as follows: visus oculi dextri (VOD) sine correctione (sc) 1.0, visus oculi sinistri (VOS) sine correctione (sc) 0.5, left bulbus in exodeviation of 10 PD with convergence insufficiency, double vision in the direction of looking straight, occasionally in elevation and depression, with no double vision in the terminal abduction right and left. The girl did not notice the pain. The pupil was in the mydriasis with a very slow motion in the light. Other status of the anterior eye segment as well as of the eye fundus was normal. A computed tomography scan showed a metallic foreign body in the left orbital conus, without fractures or intracranial intrusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Immediate tetanus prophylaxis, antimicrobial therapy (amoxicillin/clavulanic acid, metronidazole), neuroprotective therapy (methylprednisolone) and local therapy (tobramycinum) were introduced. Given the high risk of surgical treatment, the girl was conservatively treated and monitored. The girl was relieved of physical activity at school due to the possibility of moving the foreign body. Three years after the injury, the girl has only a pupil in semi mydriasis and a slower reaction to direct light. The visual acuity is as follows: VOD sc 1.0, VOS sc 0.9. Other eye status is normal.</p>
         <fig position="anchor" id="fig1">
            <label>Figure 1:</label>
            <caption>
               <p> Skull x-ray with a foreign body (bullet) in the left orbit (AP and LL projection)</p>
            </caption>
            <p>
               <graphic xlink:href="2963-web-resources/image/zdravvestn-2963-sl-01.png"/>
            </p>
         </fig>
         <fig position="anchor" id="fig2">
            <label>Figure 2:</label>
            <caption>
               <p> Computed tomography - metallic foreign body (bullet) in the left orbital conus, without fractures or intracranial intrusion</p>
            </caption>
            <p>
               <graphic xlink:href="2963-web-resources/image/zdravvestn-2963-sl-02.png"/>
            </p>
         </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3" sec-type="Discussion">
         <label>3</label>
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>In spite of the fact that intraorbital foreign bodies (IOrbFbs) are associated with serious ocular and orbital injuries (ocular injuries are both more common and serious in patients with posteriorly located foreign bodies) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>), we show a case in which this statement is not entirely correct. By reviewing the literature, we have determined that this is the first described case with regard to the type and position of the bullet and considering the age and sex of the child. Fulcher et al. noted that posteriorly located inorganic IOrbFbs ought not to be treated surgically, unless they are causing critical orbital complications that can irreparably harm the vision. Loss of vision is by and large related to the starting annihilating injury and is not a result of complications of the IOrbFb. In our case, the status of the eye is due to the initial compressive oculomotor nerve damage. Because of compression of the parasympathetic fibres (parasympathetic fibres act on the outside of the nerve), mydriasis (“puffy” pupil) may occur as a result of parasympathetic compression of the fibres prior to lid ptosis and “down and out” positions as a result of the motor fibres disruption. Prognosis of an oculomotor palsy depends on the aetiology. Posttraumatic oculomotor palsy may partially or completely recover spontaneously. As a possibility of complication, in a series of conservatively treated patients, one patient lost discernment of light from an optic neuropathy related to a metallic foreign body at the orbital apex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). Simon et al. affirm that retained intraorbital metallic foreign bodies are well tolerated and ordinarily have negligible adverse visual prognosis, as is the case in our patient. They support a conservative approach in the absence of specific indications for removal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). In this type of injury, attention should be paid to the chorioretinitis sclopetaria which is the result of shock waves that burst the choroid and retina, but leave the sclera intact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). As in our case, most IOrbFBs are metallic, resulting from little particles penetrating the orbit through high-velocity injury. Inorganic nonmetallic FBs are often inert. However, some metallic FBs, particularly iron, copper, and lead, can cause particular complications such as retinopathy, siderosis, chalcosis, or systemic toxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>), but there is no report where the bullet from an air rifle caused toxic side effects. Surgery may be chosen after assessment of a few parameters, such as accessibility, the organic or inorganic nature of the foreign body, anatomical relations with the optic nerve and eyeball, the infectious potential and the clinical impact of the foreign body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>). In our case, after expert counselling (neurosurgeon, ophthalmologist, maxillofacial surgeon), it was concluded that surgical removal of the bullet was not recommended due to the high risk of optic nerve damage. As with our patient, Vinodh et al. and Peralta et al. also employed the same strategy with their patient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4" sec-type="Conclusion">
         <label>4</label>
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>We concur with the fact that intraorbital metallic foreign bodies which are well tolerated and do not cause visual deterioration should be managed conservatively. So, a metallic foreign body located deep in the posterior orbit may only be observed and given appropriate supportive care, thus avoiding potential iatrogenic injury to the eye and surrounding structures.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5" sec-type="Declaration of patient consent">
         <label>5</label>
         <title>Declaration of patient consent</title>
         <p>The authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent forms. In the form, the patient’s parents have given their consent for images and other clinical information to be reported in the journal. They understand that the patient’s name and initials will not be published and due efforts will be made to conceal identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ack>
         <label>6</label>
         <title>Acknowledgment</title>
         <p>We are thankful to the family of our patient for their support and cooperation.</p>
      </ack>
      <ref-list>
         <ref id="b1">
            <label>1. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Polini</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Robiony</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Toro</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Costa</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sembronio</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Politi</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Penetrating injury of the facial skeleton through the orbit, by a massive metallic shotgun block: A case report</article-title>. 
                    <source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>. 
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <month>Oct</month>;
                    <volume>45</volume>(
                    <issue>7</issue>):
                    <fpage>586</fpage>–
                    <lpage>7</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjoms.2006.08.007</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17027129</pub-id>
                    <issn>0266-4356</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b2">
            <label>2. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dimitroulis</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>An unusual bullet trajectory to the face</article-title>. 
                    <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>. 
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <month>Jan</month>;
                    <volume>64</volume>(
                    <issue>1</issue>):
                    <fpage>137</fpage>–
                    <lpage>9</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2005.09.022</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16360872</pub-id>
                    <issn>0278-2391</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b3">
            <label>3. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gönül</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Akbörü</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Izci</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Timurkaynak</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Orbital foreign bodies after penetrating gunshot wounds: retrospective analysis of 22 cases and clinical review</article-title>. 
                    <source>Minim Invasive Neurosurg</source>. 
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <month>Dec</month>;
                    <volume>42</volume>(
                    <issue>4</issue>):
                    <fpage>207</fpage>–
                    <lpage>11</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2008-1053401</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10667828</pub-id>
                    <issn>0946-7211</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b4">
            <label>4. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Finkelstein</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Legmann</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rubin</surname>
                     <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Projectile metallic foreign bodies in the orbit: a retrospective study of epidemiologic factors, management, and outcomes</article-title>. 
                    <source>Ophthalmology</source>. 
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <month>Jan</month>;
                    <volume>104</volume>(
                    <issue>1</issue>):
                    <fpage>96</fpage>–
                    <lpage>103</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0161-6420(97)30355-8</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9022111</pub-id>
                    <issn>0161-6420</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b5">
            <label>5. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fulcher</surname>
                     <given-names>TP</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>McNab</surname>
                     <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                     <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Clinical features and management of intraorbital foreign bodies</article-title>. 
                    <source>Ophthalmology</source>. 
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <month>Mar</month>;
                    <volume>109</volume>(
                    <issue>3</issue>):
                    <fpage>494</fpage>–
                    <lpage>500</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0161-6420(01)00982-4</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11874750</pub-id>
                    <issn>0161-6420</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b6">
            <label>6. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ben Simon</surname>
                     <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Moisseiev</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rosen</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Alhalel</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Gunshot wound to the eye and orbit: a descriptive case series and literature review</article-title>. 
                    <source>J Trauma</source>. 
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <month>Sep</month>;
                    <volume>71</volume>(
                    <issue>3</issue>):
                    <fpage>771</fpage>–
                    <lpage>8</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TA.0b013e3182255315</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909007</pub-id>
                    <issn>0022-5282</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b7">
            <label>7. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Romero-Trevejo</surname>
                     <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rachwani-Parshotam</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Morillo-Sánchez</surname>
                     <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Chorioretinitis sclopetaria caused by an intraorbital metallic foreign body</article-title>. 
                    <source>Arq Bras Oftalmol</source>. 
                    <year>2018</year>
                    <month>Jun</month>;
                    <volume>81</volume>(
                    <issue>3</issue>):
                    <fpage>247</fpage>–
                    <lpage>9</lpage>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29924198</pub-id>
                    <issn>1678-2925</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b8">
            <label>8. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pinto</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brunese</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Daniele</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Faggian</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Guarnieri</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Muto</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <etal>et al</etal>
                    </person-group>.
                    <article-title>Role of computed tomography in the assessment of intraorbital foreign bodies</article-title>. 
                    <source>Semin Ultrasound CT MR</source>. 
                    <year>2012</year>
                    <month>Oct</month>;
                    <volume>33</volume>(
                    <issue>5</issue>):
                    <fpage>392</fpage>–
                    <lpage>5</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.sult.2012.06.004</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22964405</pub-id>
                    <issn>0887-2171</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b9">
            <label>9. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Clarós</surname>
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fokouo</surname>
                     <given-names>JV</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Clarós</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Intraorbital foreign body: A rifle bullet removed 20 years after the accident</article-title>. 
                    <source>Eur Ann Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Dis</source>. 
                    <year>2017</year>
                    <month>Feb</month>;
                    <volume>134</volume>(
                    <issue>1</issue>):
                    <fpage>63</fpage>–
                    <lpage>5</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anorl.2016.04.003</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27118438</pub-id>
                    <issn>1879-7296</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b10">
            <label>10. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Koo Ng</surname>
                     <given-names>NK</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jaberoo</surname>
                     <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pulido</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Olver</surname>
                     <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Saleh</surname>
                     <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Image guidance removal of a foreign body in the orbital apex</article-title>. 
                    <source>Orbit</source>. 
                    <year>2009</year>;
                    <volume>28</volume>(
                    <issue>6</issue>):
                    <fpage>404</fpage>–
                    <lpage>7</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01676830903074087</pub-id>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19929670</pub-id>
                    <issn>0167-6830</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b11">
            <label>11. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Vinodh</surname>
                     <given-names>VP</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sellamuthu</surname>
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Harun</surname>
                     <given-names>RH</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zenian</surname>
                     <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Posterior intraorbital metallic foreign body: a case discussion</article-title>. 
                    <source>Med J Malaysia</source>. 
                    <year>2014</year>
                    <month>Apr</month>;
                    <volume>69</volume>(
                    <issue>2</issue>):
                    <fpage>89</fpage>–
                    <lpage>91</lpage>.
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25241819</pub-id>
                    <issn>0300-5283</issn>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="b12">
            <label>12. </label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Peralta</surname>
                     <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zoumalan</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>, 
                        <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lelli</surname>
                     <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                     <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                    </person-group>. 
                    <article-title>Posterior Intraorbital Foreign Body: take it or Leave it?</article-title>
                    <source>Open Reconstructive and Cosmetic Surgery</source>.
                    <year>2008</year>;
                    <volume>1</volume>(
                    <issue>1</issue>):
                    <fpage>1</fpage>–
                    <lpage>3</lpage>. 
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1876976400801010001</pub-id>
                </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
